İzlediğiniz için teşekkür ederim.
Kaldığımız evden.
Şu anda görüyorsunuz değil mi ekrana?
Evet hocam.
Tamam. Ekranda gözüküyor.
Evet.
Good morning to everybody.
Now we continue from where we left last week.
That was the slide we stopped last time I think.
Now we will have an overview of molecular biology.
At least we should know the nature of the data we are going to use.
We should know the nature of the data we are going to use.
And to deal with.
So therefore we must have a very basic introductory exposure to concepts in molecular biology.
What is the background?
Of course I am not an expert on molecular biology.
But we should have a minimal understanding at least.
moleküler biyoloji
is considered
as the study of
biyoloji at a molecular
level
this is the definition of molecular
biology is a very
big subject it covers
every living thing
but
specifically molecular biology
is the study of biology at
molecular level
the field
this molecular
biology field overlaps with
some other areas of
biology, chemistry, genetics
and biochemistry
as we see it's
bioinformatics is
always
some sort of interdisciplinary
field wherever
or whenever we
talk about something
the first
feature of
bioinformatics
is its
interdisciplinary
nature
so
in this respect molecular
biology concerns itself with
understanding the
interactions between the
various systems of a cell
including
the interactions between
DNA, RNA
and protein biosynthesis
and
and learning how these
interactions are regulated
so
Now we have here some keywords. I'm sure you already know this subject because almost all of you studied biology somehow in probably high school.
there is not
a
lot
of
info
Cell, DNA, RNA, protein, biosynthesis or whatever. These are some terminology here.
Cells, chromosomes, DNA, RNA, amino acids, proteins, genome, transcriptome, proteome.
These are some concepts we should be aware of.
We should have some knowledge about these things.
Here is an example of animal cells.
We start with cells.
I'm not going to get into more details, but at least I should remind you what a cell is.
This is a typical animal cell, which we also have this type of organisms or structures.
It's a complex system enclosed in a membrane as illustrated here.
There is a membrane and within this membrane there are
many things as
named here, some of these constituents of the cell.
The structural and functional unit of all non-living organisms.
That's a definition of a cell, kind of definition.
Structural and functional unit of all non-living organisms.
This is considered to be the smallest component of living organisms.
The smallest unit of an organism that is classified as living and is often called the building block of life.
Cell itself is a living entity.
A part of a living thing.
Living existence.
Cell itself is considered as a living entity as well.
Some organisms, such as most bacteria, are unicellular.
You know these concepts.
Prokaryotes, eukaryotes, or whatever we'll mention in a minute.
Most bacteria consist of a single cell known as unicellular.
It contains only one cell.
Other organisms have much more complex cells.
These are known as multicellular organisms.
As a human being, we have an estimated of 10 trillion cells.
10 to 14 approximately.
And 320 cell types.
The amazing thing is that the cell has a specific form, a standard form.
But different components or different tissues have different cells.
For example, eye cells.
Cells at some other parts.
Many, many different cells.
But there are approximately 320 cell types.
So typical cell size is 10 micrometer.
And its weight is 1 nanogram.
Its mass is 1 nanogram.
These are some factual quantities about the cell.
There are cell types, obviously.
Scomus cells.
Epithelial cells.
Muscle cells.
Blood cells.
cells, which includes red cells, white cells, etc.
These categorical attributes, these are categorical attributes.
You should remember the data types we mentioned when we were discussing purely data types.
We classified data types generally as categorical and numerical or non-numerical and numerical.
These are categorical attributes.
They can also be related back to numerical values, for example, number of cells or whatever.
is there are when you go for a cell blood test you get a lot of numerical values this
about blood as well the amount of the blood or whatever whatever
amount of the white blood cells red blood cells these are
numerical numerical quantities but itself whatever we said here sometimes they
count as categorical attributes
organisms can be classified into two types as i always said prokaryotes
and eukaryotes
the prokaryotes are the simpler ones which the lack a true membrane bound nucleus and organelles
these are mostly single cell
eukaryotes are more complex and contain they contain a membrane bound nucleus as we have
already seen the shape and organelles these are usually found in the blood cell
in plants animals fungi etc more advanced more developed organisms
this is a typical picture of a prokaryotic cell
i'm not going to spend much of time on this just
reminder eukaryotic cells are more complex as illustrated here these are the
constituents of the
eukaryotic cells such as nucleus
ribosome vesicle etc etc
they are usually
eukaryotic cells such as nucleus ribosome vesicle etc etc they are usually
bigger because they have more components bigger than the prokaryotes at least 10 times
and sometimes thousand times greater in volume
the main difference between prokaryotes and eukaryotes is that eukaryotic cells contain
membrane bound compartments in which specific metabolic activities take place
the shame of eukaryotic cell does other one doesn't
uh1 eukaryote's
have a nucleus this is a membrane delineated compartment that houses
the eukaryotic cells dna which we are going to talk about soon
it is this nucleus that gives the eukaryotic cellsULL
its name which means true nucleus eukaryote is true nucleus anyway all chromosomal DNA
is stored in the cell nucleus which is here which is separated from the cytoplasm by a
membrane some eukaryotic organelles such as mitochondria also contain some DNA okay
the chromosomes are important they are organized structures of DNA and proteins that are found
in cells the word itself in terms of DNA so it's sometimes called polyme, pyrex in evidence
cell it's the gene equality host but in fact the genome is at least heterogeneous
they very often hanging on so etc so they can be even more there which I call mini
the linguistic approach comes from the greek word chroma which means color and soma which
means body because of the property of being stained very strongly by some dyes that's
why it's known as chromosome as i said before the scientific words or if a scientist discovers
something so introduce a concept scientific concept usually they name it by using old
latin or greek
a chromosome is a singular piece of dna which contains many genes here we will define genes
as well later regulatory elements and other nucleotide sequences chromosomes also contain
dna bound proteins we will be talking about later which serve to package dna and control its
functions chromosomes very extensively between different organisms
the dna molecule may be circular or linear and can contain anything from tens of kilo by
kilo base pairs to hundreds of mega base pairs here we use some concepts
some concepts
will be explained later
eukaryotic cells have large chromosomes prokaryotic cells have smaller circular chromosomes
in eukaryotes nuclear chromosomes are packaged by proteins into a condensed structure which is called
chromatin this allows the
very long dna molecules to fit into this cell nucleus
chromosomes may exist as either duplicated or unduplicated
i just go faster in eukaryotis nucleus contains one of
or several double-stranded dna molecules organized as chromosomes humans have 22 pairs of
you should remember this one pair sex chromosomes
uh this is some shapes you we have here is five micrometer measure as well you can
see the sizes of these chromosomes
so here are some numbers chromosome numbers in some plants
i don't know these species but this is mazed this is
corn in corn with
wheat
bread with potato cultivated tobacco
do you see
while these say for example mazes 20 chromosomes these adders tongue fern
whatever it is i don't really know has more than thousand
chromosomes
here are some number of chromosomes in species
common fruit flyers
8 kingfishers 132 chromosome
for example
goldfishes
100-104
these were changes
from species to species
so this is a typical
structure
of
say
nucleus
nucleus have
this cell
cell has nucleus within it
the nucleus has chromosomes
when you decompose
chromosome
you have the
DNA
and base pairs
we will be discussing later
this is a different picture
the same concept
we have the DNA and we have the gene here
we have the chromosomes
then when you
untangle
we have DNA
and within DNA we have the
gene
and then we have the chromosome
base pairs
now the
DNA
DNA is
short form of
Deoxyribonucleic Acid, shortly DNA,
which is a nucleic acid that contains the genetic instructions used in the development and functioning of all non-living organisms and some viruses.
This is some sort of fingerprint of all living things.
The main role of DNA molecules is the long-term storage of information.
This is a biological information storage system.
DNA segments that carry this genetic information are called genes.
But other DNA sequences have structural purposes or are involved in regulating the use of this genetic information.
A gene DNA has several sections within a DNA information.
We'll be talking in a minute.
This has different functions, roles.
Basically, chemically, DNA consists of two long polymers of simple units, which is called nucleotides.
And these nucleotides consist of three components.
These are a nitrogenous base.
You should remember this cytosine, guanine, adenine, or thiamine.
Shortly, CGS.
These are the four bases.
Then another component is a five-carbon sugar molecule known as deoxyribose.
Then a phosphate molecule.
The backbone of the polynucleotide is a chain of sugar and phosphate molecules.
It forms a chain, basically, chemically.
Well, it may not make sense for most of us because to be able to understand this truly,
you have to be trained in chemistry, basically, especially biological chemistry.
But you can see the basic structure of these nucleotides.
A combination of these three components.
Each of the sugar groups in this sugar phosphate backbone is linked to one of the four nitrogenous bases.
This is basically sugar molecules are linking these nucleotides.
DNA's ability to store and transmit information lies in the fact that it consists of two poly nucleotide strands that twist around each other to form a double-stranded helix.
You should have already seen this in biology course. DNA is formed as base, it's called base pair. The base is linked across the two strands in a specific manner using hydrogen bonds, forms these base pairs.
We have actually two of these structures.
Double D-structures in this case.
You see these are reversed. This is 3' to 5', 5' to 3'.
Cytosine pairs with the guanine, C with G, A with T, T A.
Complementary of this will be this array.
This is the structure of, or chemical structure of DNA.
Okay, this is beyond of, beyond the scope of this.
Ama DNA'nın iki önemli özellikleri var, replik edilebilir, kopyalanabilir ve bilgiyi sürdürebilir.
Bu kopyalama işlemini daha sonra bir örnek vereceğim.
Özellikle bu virüs, bir insanın yaşadığı bir insanı doldurur.
Bu virüs çok iyi bir örnek, daha sonra bahsedeceğiz.
Bölgenin içine, DNA'nın kromozomlar denilen stüktürlerle organize edilmiştir.
Kromozomlar önce duplik edilmiştir.
Kromozomlar önce DNA replik edilmiştir.
Ukaryotik organlar, cell nucleus'un içine DNA'ları alırlar.
Ukaryotik organlar, cell sitoplasma içinde bulunur.
Bunu zaten biliyorduk.
Kromozomların içinde, kromatin proteinler, kristal, kompakt ve organize DNA'lar gibi.
Bu kompakt stüktürler, DNA ve diğer DNA'nın iletişimlerine yönelir.
DNA'nın hangi kısımları kontrol edilmiştir?
Bu konuda daha sonra bir kelime açıklayacağız.
Genetik kod, genetik malzemelerin içinde enkodulan bilgilerin,
doğal cellerden birleşen proteinlerden birleştirilmiştir.
Bu kod, genetik malzemelerin içinde enkodulan bilgilerin, doğal cellerden birleştirilmiştir.
Amino asits in an order specified by messenger RNA, which is known as mRNA.
Using transfer RNA, which is known as tRNA, molecules to carry amino acids and to read the messenger RNA, three nucleotides at a time.
Bu genetik kod, tüm organlar arasında çok benzer ve 64 adet kodla açık bir tabelde açıklanabilir.
Kod, nükleotidin çeşitli sektörleri, bu çeşitli sektörleri, kodonlar denilen tripleri şekillendirir.
Bu tripleri, protein sintezi boyutunda, amino asidi eklediğimizde eklenmektedir.
Bu,
burada açıklanmıştır.
Z-boniplik asidi var.
RNA, bu DNA gibi görünüyor.
Ama bu, bir köşedir.
Sonra bu, kodonlar hakkında değiştirilmiştir.
Kodonlar,
daha önce size bu tabeladan bahsetmedik.
3 adet gruptur.
Bu adet,
bir tanesidir.
Bir tanesi,
4 adet kemik malzemelerden bir tanesi.
Bu, kodonlar olarak bilinmiştir.
Kodonlar,
SEÑup,
Kodonlar olarak biçimli eenşel yerine gelişir.
Örneğin olur.
Beş her zaman bir haykose wardı yabanı Kodonlar olarak,
A
li Fucking
ROS
Kodr
Herkes bilir mi?
Heredite nedir?
Heredite, süreçtir.
Tamam, bir tür inheritans.
Ailemin faydalarını alırsınız.
Bu, kalıtsal.
Tamam.
Bu genler, basit, fiziksel ve fonksiyonel hereditli bir üretim üretimi.
Nükleotide bir özellik konumuna sahiptir.
nucleotides at a given position on a given chromosome that codes for a specific protein.
It consists of three types of nucleotide sequence.
First, these coding regions called exons.
Exons specify a sequence of amino acids, basically.
Then non-coding regions called introns, which do not specify an amino acid.
Then there is some regulatory sequences, which play a role in determining when and where the protein is made and how much is made.
And it looks like something like this.
We have the enhancers, promoters.
Then exon 1.
Then this is intron.
Then there is exon 2, intron.
DNA sequence is not a uniform sequence.
It looks like basically some sort of data storage in a hard disk or in a CD driver or whatever.
You have a start.
You have a start of start point, different files.
Each file has a starting point.
Sometimes some sections of the files could be in different places.
The concept is very similar here.
Now the computational challenges.
I tell you one computational challenges.
Determining this.
Regions in a DNA array is a computational challenge, basically.
So where exon 1, where it starts, where it ends.
And which part is intron.
Then exon 2, where it starts, where it finishes.
Finding these regions are computational problems.
One of my PhDs too.
I didn't basically did PhD on this.
Okay.
In most data sources, a typical representation of a DNA molecule or sequence would consist of a sequence of letters, as you already said, to represent each of the possible four nucleotides.
Which we call them base nucleotide pairs that could appear in a double helix DNA strand.
Although the DNA molecule is double stranded, the bases are paired uniquely.
There appears to be some sort of redundancy, but this is not a redundancy.
This is the structure, biological structure to store.
The information.
Is a biological information storage mechanism, basically.
This is a typical.
DNA seconds after.
Seconds.
Biochemical substance DNA.
When it seconds.
And data is.
A string, basically.
In terms of the.
Computing concept, we have all array of characters.
For you as a programmer.
DNA sequence will be.
An array of characters or a long string.
This is the first lesson.
We should deduce from this lecture.
Now, you know that the data initially you will be dealing with will be.
Text.
Character array or string.
String whichever you whichever approach you take.
This is basically an example.
Of.
Dispenser.
And.
All over.
This is the.
basically breast cancer gene which causes gene causing breast cancer or gene related to
String of the.
The process.
The string.
Which.
Or.
Attach.
Here.
Is the.
String.
breast cancer one of the problems in bioinformatics computational problems identifying genes
And the string.
This.
String.
You will learn from this.
This is the string.
This.
String.
That.
Is the.
String.
or relations of certain genes with certain diseases
so that's another challenge you know just there are many genes and which gene causes what disease
identification of this is a computational challenge people are always searching functions of genes or
some existing genes relationship to some health conditions
is another computational challenge
we already said there are four possible bases acgu each combination of three nucleotides
was called a codon in this respect there are four over three because we have triplets codons are
basically a group of letters
containing three letters so because we have three letters and four bases it's four to three
it's similar to in binary we have two letters say i would say letters two symbols if we have
three bit we have two to three total eight com possibilities
and this approach is the same in in genetic code
instead of two we use four bases this is actually a base for system in terms of the
mathematical concepts we have a base for system because we in codons we have
three letters we have total 64 possible codon sequences
and if we have such a base so we can go from one of these to another
so basically we have two different types oféta of a single protein
and in this case we have two different types oféta i mean one is a B quedone
we say that one is a B quedone and another one is an L quedone
we have in the special case there are six components
If this codon appears in a genetic or DNA array, it indicates a start of information, I would say.
These are AUG and stop codons.
Whenever we encounter these codons in a DNA array, then that information finishes there, it stops there.
And these are not only one, three different ones, UAA, UAG, and UGA.
Basically, this is a pattern.
For example,
You want to have a DNA.
You want to identify how many different information sections exist in DNA array.
Probably, you should search for AUG pattern in a DNA array.
You have basically string or character array.
You will take this character array, or if you take it as a string,
Within this string, you will be searching UAUG pattern.
Whenever you identify this pattern, then you will label it as a start position, start codon.
Well, at that position, an information starts.
61 codons to code for amino acids.
There are basically 20 amino acids total used biologically, not 61, total 20.
That means there are redundancy in genetic code.
For most of the amino acids, there are several codons that represent the same amino acid.
This probably explains, you know, the material or protein process is exactly the same, but end result is different proteins, different cells.
That might be due to these redundancies.
As an example, the amino acid list.
Leucine is represented by two codons.
The first one is 3A and AAG.
And leucine is represented by any one of six different combinations.
Here is the 20 amino acids.
Total, we have 20.
Here's a table.
We have glycine, alanine, valine, leucine, etc., etc.
And these are the...
Short.
The first form and the corresponding letter.
When we form, construct amino acid sequences, we will be using a combination of these 20 letters to express a genetic information in the form of amino acid sequences rather than DNA sequences.
By doing...
By doing this, depending on what we are looking for, we may get more information.
Sometimes, it's better to consider in analysis, it is better to consider DNA sequence.
And in some cases, it might be better to consider amino acid sequences.
Okay.
Okay, these are 20.
amino acids now the another type of data you will be dealing with is amino acid sequences
again in terms of the character array or string
now instead of an array which will be a combination of only four letters this is dna
a text array now you will have an array which
is a combination of 20 letters this is again a character array or a string to deal with
so amino acids are the basic structure of wilding units of proteins you already know this
we can classify them as hydrophilic amino acids which are water soluble or hydrophilic
hydrophobic, which are not water soluble. These are some properties. There are, they have more properties, but for the time being, we should not include this sort of information. Later, we may need some, to deal with some extra properties.
For example, this hydrophilic or hydrophobic properties might be used in further analysis, or there are some other options to classify them. We'll be discussing these properties later, when we discuss the methods for analysis.
Thank you.
Now, the process of formation from an mRNA template is known as translation will be describing
these concepts formula later 20 amino acids are encoded by the standard genetic code and
are called proteinogenic or standard amino acids.
Some other amino acids contained in proteins are usually formed by post translation modification,
which is modification of the translation in protein synthesis.
These modifications are often essential for the function or regulation of a protein.
Now,
how does this code work?
I try to explain graphically.
This is a template for construction of proteins.
We have this double standard DNA through some processes.
This process is summarized here.
We have the DNA.
DNA is unzipped through a process known as transcription.
Then we have messenger RNA.
It carries the code to the DNA to be formed.
Then we have another process known as translation, and a new protein is formed.
This is, we also mentioned this as central dogma of biology.
Then we have a complex structure as protein.
We will be talking about proteins now.
This is a large organic compound made of amino acids.
We have a combination of amino acids in a certain way, and it forms a protein.
These amino acids are arranged in a linear sequence.
chain and joined together by peptide bonds between the carboxyl and amino groups of adjacent amino
acid residues is a basically this describes a biochemical process this is beyond the scope
of this course how this happens etc but we should give you an overview the word protein again comes
from the greek word prote always which not which is primary actually we also use this for example
this is prototype you know what a prototype is when you prototype something pro is has same
meaning as here
the sequence of amino acids in a protein is defined by a gene and encoded in the genetic code
essential parts of organisms and participate in every process of within cells these are
reference to proteins proteins are essential parts of organisms
it for example proteins in your muscle
allows you to move this is what your body needs basically protein is what your body needs
to have energy it's it's a source of energy
for for a living thing
we need protein to be able to move to be able to do anything basically so this is so important
but it also needs this also are most important once you consider these things
that's it is important to integrate protein in all the therapies at all sets the study
of protein
serving as signals. Proteins also are components of cell and
tissue structure. Many hundreds of thousands of proteins found in living organisms have been
named, cataloged, and their properties are recorded. And these properties are the functions
of the protein, the gene that codes for it, diseases that may relate to its absence or
mutation. These are another type of information you may be dealing with in the computational
context, the properties of the protein in terms of the categorical attributes.
Other proteins are important in cell signaling, as we already said, such as hormones, kinases,
immune responses, cell adhesion, and the cell cycle, or the transport of energy and oxygen.
Proteins are also necessary in animals' diets. Since animals cannot synthesize all the amino
acids they need and must obtain essential amino acids from food, what happens? Through
the process of digestion, animals, human beings as well, break down ingested protein into
three amino acids.
Proteins are then used in metabolism. So we need protein as a source of energy.
Here we have an example of how this DNA information is used by viruses, for example HIV virus.
Here we see.
Uh,
a graphical or pictorial description of the multiplication of hiv virus how hiv virus infects
a living cell and makes copies of its own
first the cell is exposed to virus
so virus infects the cell at the first stage it enters the virus
the second hiv enters your first it enters your body then hiv at the second step enters
into cell this is also the valid for the this covet
infection case as well hiv enters your cell then your own cell
reads the hiv code
at the third stage
and creates the hiv protein through the process we have already described the protein creation process
transcription
and translation and protein creation once any actually the virus itself is not capable of
duplicating itself it gets itself duplicated by your own cell then one cell infects one virus
infects itself
cell and many copies are produced within your own cell through this protein
synthesis process then the new viral proteins prepare hiv for infection of other cells by
leaving now they they invade the cell and make many copies of its own then
they leave the cell to infect others this is how multiplies virus
if you do not prevent this process then
you usually die because of infections because it will
trigger
complicated processes within the body and these may be harmful for the health
of your body and you eventually die actually the
main purpose of virus is not to kill you it wants survive it's just your it wants your body to
survive to multiply to live on so virus would not like host to die basically but the this process
triggers many complicated undesired activities within body that it causes death
so it is possible to prevent this process
so many drugs are basically targeting to prevent this multiplication process of a virus
in this case it was hiv so if you prevent this virus docking to cell
somehow
if you disable this copying process then you stop the virus multiplication
this is what many drugs are trying to do and these drugs are known as inhibitors
so these drugs basically
bind to proteins
to bacteria
and acid
terbis
to this
inactivated
with
peptide
creatinine
actиля
or
carbide
peptide
because
they're
two
different
what
docks into a cell and prevents the virus to attach to the cell then
the process of multiplication and infection will be finished
protease is an enzyme which breaks down proteins and peptides basically
let's have a break
we start
in 10 minutes
you
Altyazı M.K.
And basically, it is related to target identification.
Actually, this stage tries to answer the question, what protein can we attack to stop the disease from progressing?
Which another important stage is leading to discovery and optimization.
What sort of molecule will bind to this protein?
Drug discovery process includes first target identification and discovery and optimization.
Then the toxicology, as you remember, we mentioned this toxicology as part of fields within the bioinformatics.
Basically, it is related to...
Answering the questions, does it kill the patient?
Side effects.
You have the drug and it must not have the side effect.
Or does it have a side effect?
So, does it get to the problem spots?
These are the questions dealt with in drug discovery.
So, in the past...
We put some of the infectious agent into thousands of tiny wells.
Then add a non-drug-led compound into each well.
Try nearly every drug-led known.
That's the past approach.
But present or current approach is see the...
Then we try to see...
Try to see...
Try to see which one kills the agent.
This requires many, many trials.
In this case, we have too small to see.
So, we have to use chemical test called assays.
This is a biochemical process performed in the labs.
This is beyond the scope of our interest.
Actually, this is important, of course.
They call it wet lab.
Actually...
It is biochemical testing performed by experts in chemistry in labs.
But our approach is computational screening.
We have different pieces of the puzzle.
We are trying to fit into the correct place.
Okay.
The...
I have already mentioned some problems in bioinformatics.
But generally, problems are classified into several groups.
The genomics.
It is a problem of gene findings.
It's a field of bioinformatics which deals with gene finding.
And annotation.
Annotation.
is with labeling it or whatever this is basically the sequence alignment and database search
it's required we will be talking about the sequence alignment and database search is basically a
interest of country engineers
another problem is functional genomics we have the microarray expressions
this produces huge amounts of
data
through the utilization of gene chips proton mix is another field
which deals with the proton protein level studying protein level structures
this is one of the field structure prediction it requires comparative modeling and function
prediction and it requires further analysis of say for example gene interactions protein interactions
or whatever and the structural bioinformatics which deals with molecular docking which i have
already given an example and screening etc
what about the overall
study of an organism's entire genome. We mentioned this several times, but there is no harm in
repeating. The field includes intensive efforts to determine the entire DNA sequence of organisms
general mix is that
and fine-scale genetic mapping efforts. This field is, in fact, is already very developed,
it will mostly relate to the
telomukes
to the
izers
very advanced. For the United States Environmental Protection Agency, for example, the term
so
the
ketogenics
genomics encompasses a broader scope of scientific inquiry and associated technologies
than when genomics was initially considered. Now it has broader meaning. We already
said what a genome was. Here is another description. A genome is the total of all
an individual organism's genes.
Thus, genomics is the study of all the genes of a cell or tissue at the DNA or microRNA,
messenger RNA, transcriptome, after transcriptome, this is what we have, or protein levels, which
is known as proteome. After translation, we have the protein.
Proteomics is the large-scale study of proteins, particularly their structures and functions.
As we already described, proteins are vital parts of living organisms, as they are the
main components of the physiological metabolic pathways of cells.
The term proteomics was going to make an analogy with genomics, which was study of the
genes. Proteomics is study of the proteins, basically.
Proteon is the entire complement of proteins, including the modifications made to a particular
set of proteins.
proteins produced by organism or system time and distinct requirements or stresses that a cell or
organism undergoes structural bioinformatics refers to the branch of bioinformatics which
is related to the analysis and prediction of the three-dimensional structure of a biological
micro molecules such as proteins the term structure has the same meaning as in structural
biology and structural bioinformatics can be seen as computational structural structural biology
we mentioned air and a
ribonucleic acid is a nucleic acid
that is it
contains a long
chain of nucleotide units each nucleotide consists of a
nitrogenous base a ribose sugar and a phosphate similar to DNA
but it is different than the DNA in the following aspects in the cell RNA is usually single-stranded
DNA is double-stranded
RNA
nucleotides contain ribose DNA contains deoxyribose
RNA has the base uracil
rather than thiamine which is present in DNA
RNA is transcribed from DNA by enzymes called RNA polymerizes and is generally further processed by other enzymes
RNA is central to the synthesis of proteins actually RNA is a byproduct of the process of
protein synthesis or the I wouldn't say byproduct is
intermediate product
during this process there are RNAs with other roles in particular regulating
which genes are expressed but also as the genome of most viruses so knowing this information is
so
example
n
important when within the bioinformatics computational bioinformatics context
dealing with these databases there will be rna databases dna databases amino acid databases
n
protein databases messenger rna
basically as name implies it carries information from dna to structures called ribosomes
it carries messages these ribosomes are made from proteins and ribosomal rna's
which come together to form a molecular machine that can read
you
messenger RNAs and translate the information they carry into proteins. This is actually
the part of the process which I have given you an example as an example this HIV virus generation.
Linear molecule encoding genetic information copied from DNA molecules. The process
is known as transcription.
This is a process in which DNA is copied into an RNA molecule. The message from DNA is
transferred to RNA through transcription by messenger RNAs.
Eukaryotic genes can be pieced together. These pieces are exons and introns as I already said.
Messenger RNA processing removes introns and splices exons
together. Now that's another challenge. Basically
in when you model this process actually this is done biochemically through protein synthesis but
if you want to model this protein synthesis as a computational model first you have to
you have a character array or string array DNA or amino acid whatever DNA array okay
you obtained from a structure now you want to identify exons and introns
to be able to this actually you want to find the actual information to be able to do this. You have
to perform a computational process known as splice site identification now splicing operation
biochemically is removing introns from this dna rna dna array and joining these exons
which are the coding regions information con containing regions for specific purposes
this process is known as splice site detection and splicing
joining introns together removing sorry removing introns and joining exons to form a complete
information array
processed messenger rna can be translated into a protein sequence then so if you want
to model this process then we have to be able to deal with this process computation
and it includes many algorithmic approaches
here is a picture we have the exons
and we have the introns then we have the termination sites basically the computational
challenges to identify these starting and ending points for each these different sections
you just try to combine into a single array these blue ones say in this case
these are for example red ones here are
exons
attend whatever you model you build should take such a file
and identify these borders
and eliminate these sections and join only these red ones to form
a messenger rna information content of dna array
by saying information content of
dna
i do not mean that other regions are useless they have different purposes
in fact in the past they used to say that dna in a human being 94 90 90 percent of dna
considered was considered as junk
useless but the reason for this is because they do not
understand
what these 90 percent of dna section represent or we don't know therefore we call it chunk
but we are learning more and more and we do not call them junk anymore
t rna is transfer rna
Basically, this is a small RNA which is usually about 74 to 95 nucleotides, quite small.
It transfers a specific amino acid to a growing polypeptide chain at the ribosomal site of
protein synthesis during translation.
It has a 3' terminal site for amino acid attachment.
This covalent linkage is catalyzed by an aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase.
It also contains a tree-based region called the anticodon that can base pair to the corresponding
tree-based codon region on mRNA.
Each type of
.
Transfer RNA molecule can be attached to only one type of amino acid, but because the
genetic code contains multiple codons that specify the same amino acid, transfer RNA
molecules bearing different anticodons may also carry the same amino acid.
These are well-defined three-dimensional structures basically and it is critical for
creation of proteins.
this part of the central dogma process basically
the process translation
is a process in which the nucleotide sequence of the processed messenger lna is used in order to
join amino acids together into a protein with the help of ribosomes and transfer lna
so to sum up all these things we define the processes and central
dogma actually we try to give the processes individually
for
forming the central dogma we have the dna we have the replication process
we have the information passed to rna
through transcription this is the rna synthesis and we have the
translation process to synthesize a new protein this is how proteins are formed
so this is not important right now because we can always do our studies
on a different body sort of and uh to clarify whatresponseing is
so
we have already defined what gene was and what a genome was gene is the physical and functional
unit of heredity that carries information from one generation to the next a genome is an organism's
so
yes
complete set of dna including all of its genes each genome contains all of the information
needed to build and maintain that organism genome size and number of genes does not necessarily
determine organisms complexity here are some genome comparisons humans have 23 chromosomes
this is the genome size and number of genes is approximately 30 000
is the mouse almost very similar to human being therefore therefore many experiments
drug experiments are performed first on the mouse then if it is successful they continue to
experiments on humans there are many similarities with human mouse
biological structure
and human being and usually mouse is used for accelerated lab tests for example a test in human
beings say which could take years that could be done on a mouse in within months this is free fly
and this is yeast
this is corn
etc
we have already described transcriptome
proton
a transcriptome is complete collection of all possible messenger
RNAs
proton is complete collection of proteins
that can be produced by an organism
so after giving these fundamental concepts
the related to
biology or structural or computational biology or molecular biology now we can try to relate to
representation of all this information in a computer i have already given you data
representation as a fundamental concept we know how to represent the data in a computing system
but specifically within the context of computational biology or molecular biology
we also need to discuss what can be represented in a computer we need to really relate
these fundamental terminology or concepts into computational context
in order for
programs to deal with biomedical data the data must be encoded according to
some plan so that the binary numbers in the computers memory represent numeric
data or represent text or possibly more abstract kinds of data which we named it
as coding either we have to represent a quantity or represent a quality we
already discussed this many encoding schemes have been used for biomedical
data so the first examples would be biomolecular sequence data
and proteins
we always
I already hinted how to represent it, these are basically characters or string.
which is some sort of coding must be used to represent these characters we have already
described how to represent characters in a computing system it's just basically ASCII
character codes we will be using to represent these DNA codes and amino acid codes because
to represent these biochemical structures in terms of the understandable format we use
letters written on the paper in the past that was how these information are recorded
just they were written as a text file in the papers
now
they need
to be saved in the computer in terms of the character, so that will be ASCII coded data.
Or laboratory data from tests done on blood samples and other substances obtained from
patients in a clinic or hospital and medical image data. These are kind of data. These some
results. After blood test, some results are quantitative, say for example number of blood cells
or amount of some blood components in a sample of blood. These are numerical data and we will
be using either integers or in most cases we will be using floating point data.
To represent them and sometimes
some categorical data might also be produced. For example, rather than numerical, we can say that
in a certain volume of blood, you can say that red blood cells are
very small.
Middle amount or very high or whatever. Now we have categorical data.
Or medical image. Medical image usually will be in terms of the pixel representation.
In some cases we will have voxels, volumetric pixels, which is video or moving
images and we call it moving images.
And we call it movie or video.
And we will use probably color representation. Each pixel will be
an integer and that integer will represent a color. This will be a code.
Yes, it will be an integer binary integer, but it will represent a code rather than a quantity.
for example
so in addition everyone needs
methods for searching and sorting
through the vast collections
of bibliographic reference
data now available
such as the Medline database
of journal articles and other
information items
so this
the data
obtained from this will be
basically it could be
text within this
text it could be some numerical
representations
the computational
challenge in this case is
searching these
bibliography
references
literature
and extracting the information
certain patterns
whatever we are searching for
and this requires
some
problems
probably NLP techniques
natural language processing techniques
so the entries in such bibliographic
databases are definitely
not numeric as i said
some are keywords but we can also
search for some numerical
data there
so
in a typical
contrast encoding each letter is
represented
by its ASCII code. We already said this. Base sequences as letter sequences or long strings.
Another way to represent such sequences is to represent each nucleotide as a symbol in a list.
The entire sequence then becomes a list of symbols and looks like this basically. This is the most
thanks
common data type we will be dealing with within this course. This is a typical DNA data array.
Large digital data repositories are available containing information about proteins.
Here are some names. Probably we will mention some of them in detail.
Uniprotein
Uniprotein, Swissprotein, Knowledgebase.
These Uniprotein data are downloadable in a variety of formats.
They have data formats, certain formats from this website. It is maintained by
Swiss Institute for Bioinformatics. Here we have a next slide. In the next slide we have
a small excerpt from Swissprotein tree, for the precursor protein from which human insulin is formed.
Of course, there are a lot of codes here used to represent this data. It has metadata as well.
Most of the information that we just discussed.
information or here you see forms metadata
actual sequence starts at the end of
this picture
of course we are not going to spend much time to explain all of these fields but i give you some
of the fields what they are for example dr records are cross references dr here where is dr here
these are cross references
in this case to the gene ontology
ft records are future
descriptor the descriptions
some of the features shown here are the places
in the amino acid sequence where different types of structures occur
then the names following the ft tags are the feature types
the numbers are the second start and end points for each feature
finally the sq section contains the actual seconds of amino acids one letter for each
which is go back here
now when you read such a data
to process the you can extract a lot of information
about this data through these metadata so
then before processing this text data probably you need to remove all this metadata and
just concentrate on this sq part
you can see computation you can see the problems and what you should do basically you need to pass
this data if we want to use the term regular expression terms
okay
so
many proteins function as enzymes as we already said
the next slide shows an example a small excerpt from the enzyme database
Here, for example, the line beginning with ID is the enzyme commission number.
It is unique to each entry. The DE line is the official name.
This is malate dehydrogenase, whatever it is.
AN lines are alternative names or synonyms, alternative names.
I skip these. CC line is a comment. What was the comment?
Let's see. It's a comment. It is explanation, basically.
Then we have PI.
PR line is a cross reference to the Procide database.
DR line is a set of cross references to entries in the Swisspro database.
Probably DR is short for data reference.
I'm not sure. So we might want to study one gene protein,
DNA molecule or other type of objects in a database.
For example, for human beta globin, there is a gene known as HPB,
which stands for homoglobin subunit beta.
I don't know what they are, but a protein.
This is a protein sequence, a protein structure and entries for various kinds of variations.
We can think about large groups such as all the globin genes in the human genome or all the non-HPB variants.
Or we might want.
To study a set of 100 genes previously implicated in a disease to assess their variation in a patient samples.
These are different ways of thinking about searching the database.
Well, in database, you will find many, not a single simple information,
but a combination of information depending on what you are looking for.
You will design your algorithm to extract this information from the existing databases.
There are biological databases.
Since the study started, people started storing, saving this collected information.
Data.
Data banks.
There are three main sites that have been responsible for storing nucleotide sequence data from 1982 to the present.
The first one is GenBank.
This is at the National Center for Biotechnology Information, shortly NCBI.
Database.
The European Molecular Biology Laboratory, which is known as EMBL.
Bank.
Nucleotide sequence database.
Part of the European Nucleotide Archive at the European Bioinformatics Institute in Kingston, England.
And there is DNA Database of Japan, VVBJ, at the National Institute of Genetics in Machine Learning.
These are three main data banks.
A lot of data can be obtained from these sources.
INSTC coordinate sequence data.
INSTC is International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration.
We have GenBank.
We have already described INA and VVBJ.
The nucleotide collections of GenBank at the NCBI, EMBL Bank at the European Bioinformatics Institute and VVBJ at the Japan are all coordinated by International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration.
NCBI organization is given here.
Of course, these are completely big subjects.
What is the structure?
I am just referring to you if you are going to get some data.
Bu sistemde 40 molekül ve literatür bilgisayarları var.
Gembank, TraceArchive ve SequenceReadArchive var.
Gembank'ta nükleotide, genom sorumluluk sektörleri ve ekspres sektörleri var.
40 molekül ve literatür bilgisayarlarından bir parçaya sahiptir.
Bu, Avrupa Biyoinformatik Üniversitesi'nin bilgisayar stüktürü var.
Burada farklı bölümler var.
Bu, Avrupa Biyoinformatik Üniversitesi'nin bilgisayar stüktürü.
1982'den beri bu bilgisayarların sayısı çok yüksek.
Bu sayıda, bu bilgisayarların sayısı çok yüksek.
Bu sayısı, 1985, 1982'den 2016'dan doğruyu bulunuyor.
Bu bizim gezegen Kafka Fenomeni見 faux tarif.
Laptop olarak ss裡面 bir diğer merkezden delesik,
woluf olarak parçalar ve benzetik merkez aşağı yüzeylerineполendirebilir.
genetik gelişim teknolojisi
1 base pair is abbreviated as 1 base pair actually this is information given in this
representation they use 1 kilobase megabase gigabase terabase pair petabase pair these
are the correct measures used let's have a second break here
start at 11.5
Altyazı M.K.
exabytes 10 to 18. This says the file sizes. Can anybody tell me the problem in this slide?
Can anybody tell me if there is any problem in these slides or not?
And not only this book, I have seen this in some other books.
Can anybody tell me the problem in this slide?
I did not prepare this.
I took it from
a book, a book has slides and I just simply copied from there.
Can anybody tell me if there is any problem or not in this slide?
Okay, it's KB should be KB.
This is not really a problem.
Well, that's a good question for Chris.
Actually, I have written the author saying that there is a problem in this slide and
he agreed.
Okay.
Let's go on here.
What is the problem?
.
?
Now the problemظ todas
is according to me this is incorrect and it's already the the author of the the book is already
informed and he agreed that was a book on bioinformatics i saw the same problem on a book
written about management information system because in the past i have already given this
course and i used some books but apparently i saw the same mistake there now i give you the
measures of speed and capacity in a computing system
in computing systems to describe a computing system's performance
we describe performance in a computing system exactly alias got the point
one thousand one kilo is we use decimal if we are talking about speed or whatever but we use
the binary two to power whatever if we are talking about the capacity if i go back the author the
professor who have who who written that book was talking about this scales of file sizes in a
computing system if you are talking about
sizes you have to use the right metric and this is completely wrong and you will see this in the
books quite you will not see in a computing books compute architecture or logic books or whatever
but you will see in the books who which are written by the
authors who does not have a background in computing system if they somehow
want to give information about some computing related concepts they usually make such mistakes
so the correct metric he should be using is this one and now if we correct this one is
well one is correct two to zero is one but
Bir sonraki de 2-10, 2-20, 2-30, 2-40, 2-50, 2-60 olur.
Tamam mı?
2-10, 2-10, 2-10, 2-10, 2-10 이것 universes.
10-3 ve 10-2, 2-10 değil.
Biri 1000, diğeri de 1024.
Yani, Ali Aksaf deix.
Bu önemliydi çünkü bu çok ehsizedir.
Yani, bir çizgi, öğrenmek için deformation muzsaka u такое et güçlendiğiniz ısrarla dolul innocent 일반 eğнутürlenip kodedilir.
İzlediğiniz için teşekkür ederim.
Bu arada, taksamın ne demek olduğunu zannediyorsunuz.
Taksam, taksamın bir grupları veya bir biyolojik klasifikasyonunda bir kutu olan bir taksam.
Taksam, bir biyolojik klasifikasyonunda bir kutu olan bir taksam.
Taksam, bir biyolojik klasifikasyonunda bir taksam.
İzlediğiniz için teşekkür ederim.
...data basınca, DNA ya da protein data basınca olabilirsiniz.
Ama protein, genellikle bu proseslerle ilgili DNA data basınca,
...transkript, splice ve transkript olarak.
Daha önce de söylediğim gibi, protein modelini model etmek istiyorsanız,
...bu prosesleri kutlamak zorundasınız.
Çünkü tesislerde, laplarda, genellikle...
...DNA, protein bilgisayarını okumak zorundasınız.
Ne yapıyoruz?
DNA bilgisayarını okuyoruz ve bu DNA bilgisayarından...
...protein okumak prosesini model edebilirsiniz.
Unigan Database, bir örnek.
Burada birkaç slayt göstereceğim.
Tesisler hakkında.
Daha fazla zaman kutlamak istemiyorum.
Ama anladın mı?
Bence...
...buradaki...
...tesisler...
...Taxonomy Browser'ın...
...Taxonomy Browser'ın bir araç.
Bu araç, tesislerdeki...
...data okuyabilmenizi sağlar.
Birçok araç var.
Burada...
...2. yöntem kullanıyoruz.
Hayır, 1. yöntem.
2. yöntem kullanıyoruz.
Tesislerdeki...
...data okumak için hazırlanmış araçlar kullanabilirsiniz.
We mentioned some of these concepts, accession number, etc.
Let's identify the following components, complete genome, complete chromosome, then we have genomic contic, messenger RNA, protein, NP, etc.
How to access the sequences?
You can use an example of query for beta globin again using a tool from NCBI.
These are just screen captures.
This is another.
Screen capture in FASTA format.
FASTA is a format.
It is the human data from human beings, homo sapiens.
Among globins, you will need beta, we mentioned before.
We mentioned genome browsers.
These are the tools.
Versatile.
Tools to visualize chromosomal positions with annotation tracks.
They are useful to explore data related to some chromosomal feature of interest, such as gene.
There are ensemble UCSC and NCBI provided tools.
There are hundreds of specialized genome browsers.
There are thousands of databases on the internet.
But if you want to see some examples of how genome browsers function, you can also visit the NCBI website.
If you are looking for an example of another genome browser, you can look for the NCBI website.
This is from UCSC.
The NCBI has several databases.
This is a web-based genome browser.
The NCBI is a big genomic genetic source.
It's very easy to use.
It's easy to use.
You can query some data there.
And
some visualization examples.
If you are interested, you can
explore some of these tools and
how it works, what they do.
So,
however, it is
important that when you search for information
about a particular gene,
you want to make sure that you know the official
gene symbol and choose the appropriate species.
You have to have a background on this molecular biology.
Therefore,
I will just cover this subject.
So,
the field of bioinformatics is
still growing quite fast.
In part because of the introduction of vast
amounts of sequence data.
With the introduction of these
modern
sequencing
techniques.
There are many databases that
store genomic data and many
approaches to extracting information.
So,
you have to know these
tools or
you have to know this type of
data to be able to deal with.
Any
question?
Regarding these subjects?
Now, the lesson from this lesson is you have to know the properties of the data you are
dealing with, including the format, including the metric units, everything.
So this is important because the prior condition before starting any analysis is to have a good data.
If you don't have a good data, appropriate data, which we already described the properties of a good data.
Then there's no point of applying analysis techniques because you will never get the desired result.
Okay.
Now, before introducing the.
Algorithmic approaches to this DNA analysis.
is we need to define the technical environment in this respect the i will try to introduce
the some computing concepts and traditionally we were
using per language in this course time permitting i will also include as an introduction to python
but not this week maybe next week or whenever i prepare and prepare a presentation on python
first we start
with some technical introduction then i will introduce the per language
because i am not giving a pearl completely
at least you can deal with per and we slowly change the python
okay
if there is no comment or no question we start new subject
i will introduce the learning objectives of this lecture is that you will understand
segments iteration and selection processes you have already known this but i will remind you
basic building blocks of programming and the three is constant commands and conditions use of words and words
of variable containers, these are some Perl operators
and this pattern matching technology.
Probably so far you have seen,
you have studied the Java C,
maybe C++ or C sharp, I'm not sure,
but the Perl has some properties
which are similar to Python as well.
Python and Perl are different,
but they have common properties
as they are both scripting languages
or they can use the scripting languages.
And at least with Perl, we'll be able to see
a different aspect of programming language
within this context.
Now, Perl is quite old,
but still extensively used in bioinformatics.
So it's good to have an exposure.
So to set the technological scheme,
of course, one of the objectives of this course
to enable students to acquire an understanding of and ability.
programming language but we have already know these concepts assuming that this course is also
open to non-computing students that should be given as well
as we already know modern computers are organized around two main components what are these
what are the in most general way what are the two main components of computers
okay hardware and software exactly hardware and software these are the most general the
in terms of the system
most general two components of a system the to be able to call
a system a computer it must have a hardware and it must have a software normally a computer is
composed of several layers or we assume that it has several several layers some layers
falls within this software the
i wouldn't say some there is only one layer for the hardware okay
so all computers given enough time and memory are capable of computing
exactly the same thing this is the most important property of a computing system
whether it is the smallest calculator or a supercomputer so both
do the same
job for the same problem
if they give different results then one of them is wrong or malfunctions it means okay
two two two plus two should make four a calculator will give you this you ask the
supercomputer two plus two it will give you the same result this is one of the fundamental
common properties of all computing devices
in theory computer can compute anything
which is possible to compute
given enough memory and time
for a problem if you use pda or your smartphone probably takes months for a complex problem
in order to solve a complex scientific problem you give it to a super computer it will
give you the result within fraction of seconds
in practice solving problems involves computer under constraints what we don't have that luxury
you know just we don't have enough we never have enough memory in many cases and enough time
And these are the two basic constraints in computing system.
And there are some extra constraints.
The time is the first one.
We should get the result as soon as possible.
For example, take weather forecasting.
You have the past information.
You gave it to a computing system.
You want to forecast or guess tomorrow's weather.
Or if you get the result after two days, there is no point of having this calculation.
It must give me the tomorrow's weather forecasting as soon as possible, before tomorrow arrives.
So this is the time.
Time is money.
Or if you have an animation, you are running an animation,
it should look like animation.
It should look like a real action.
So if it waits, next move waits, then it will not give you the sense of real action.
The cost, another thing is cost constraint.
It should be affordable.
Then another one is power.
This is if.
Mobility is a critical requirement.
bir uygulama için, o zaman güçler çok çok önemli. Özellikle kendiliğe sahip olan
See more details about the next slide and subscribe to the channel.
kompüterler veya laptoplar için. Örneğin, bir sürü güç almak istiyorsanız, o
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
güçler hiç duramayacak. Ama bu imkansız. Yani güç, önemli bir
arayış. Teknoloji, bilgisayarlar olarak belirlenilebilir. Toplamda,
aplicasyonlar, araçlar, operasyon sistemleri var.
Teknoloji, bilgisayarlar olarak belirlenilebilir. Toplamda, aplikasyonlar, araçlar, operasyon sistemleri var.
Bu araçlar, bu araçlar ve biz de araçlarımız var.
Araçlar, genellikle dışarıdaki devletler veya dünyanın dışında olan araçlar.
İndianın deneyim sisteminin içerikli üzerinde, giriş-düstrağın, k COP ţz ile dair.
Üzerlerle derinleştirilir.
Aslında bunlar da kullanıcılar.
Ayrıca masin de iletişim edebilir.
Örneğin,
say embedded system, if it is part of a smart car, controlled by a computer, the computing system will interact with the car's other components,
like the driving mechanism, gas mechanism or whatever, then it will have different components here.
But in a normal computing system, assuming that end user is, or the outside world is formed by a user or another computer,
then probably network is responsible to make interface between another computer and the existing computing system.
Perfect.
Sprinter or keyboard or screen mouse enables a computing system to interact with end user.
Anyway.
Operating system interacts directly with the hardware.
It's responsible for ensuring efficient use of hardware resources.
Tools are basically...
...softwares that take advantage of what the operating system has to offer.
Usually the applications are developed using these tools, because tools will enable to access to the resources of the computing system to the programmer.
You will be programming using these tools.
Programming languages or databases, editors, interface builders can be classified as tools.
Applications are high level, most useful category of software, because to be able to deal with or use software at that level requires a lot of skills.
You have to be a hard core computer engineer, knowledgeable engineer.
Bu noktada yine de çok fazla insan bu konuyla iletişim sistemiyle iletişim yapabiliyor.
Bu noktada iletişim sistemiyle iletişim yapabilmek için iyi bir programcı olmalısınız.
Ama çoğunlukla kullanıcılar bu noktada konuyla iletişim sistemiyle iletişim yapabilecekler.
Çünkü bu iletişim softvarları birçok konuyla iletişimciler için tasarlanmıştır.
Konuyla iletişimci olmak zorundasınız.
Eğitimci olmak zorundasınız.
Konuyla iletişim sistemiyle iletişim yapabilmek için iyi bir programcı olmalısınız.
processing anybody can use a game anybody play game even the old people or people who never
had a training in computing system
so we have algorithmic
level we have the cpu and we have the electronic level we have the problems
to formulate problems we have the algorithms
then we have the languages to implement algorithms then we have our cpu has the instruction set
architecture to enable the an algorithm coded in language
to run on a specific language
then we have the specific hardware then we have the microarchitecture
then we have the of course electrical circuits and then finally we have the
physical devices at the bottom it's a semiconductor device and it's related to physics
solid state physics and it's beyond the scope of okay we can understand
we studied electronics and micro architecture and all other levels but this is beyond the scope of
our interest and our knowledge unless you are an asic designer you have to know information or you
have to know the knowledge you have to have knowledge at that level if you want to design
actual chips
especially
if you are dealing with analog computing systems then you have to have physics
solid state physics you have to know it
as an example
a systematic sequence of transformations between layers of abstractions can be implemented
you have the problem
we have the software design we choose an algorithm
and data structure to represent that problem in a computing system we call this algorithm
then we have the programming we use a specific language to express that design
then actually we have the program
we have a process called compiling and interpreting this program is converted to
language that a processor can understand is known as machine instructions then the actual output of
this process will be an instructions a series of bits or
bytes or
words formed using bits including instruction set architecture
using the instructions from an instruction set architecture
so we can go deep to deeper as i already said
whatever
if you have if you do alt project if you want to understand this program if you doocolTextual've done
it
the problem statement is made using the natural language somebody comes to you and test the problem that's the natural language i want to this this this this and i want a program that takes these inputs and does this and gives me that result that's the problem statement
at first it may be ambiguous in precise you need to
understand actually you have learned this process in system analysis and design
in system analysis and design the first step is information gathering for requirement analysis
actually this stage refers to that a problem comes to you and you try to
understand what are the real required
to be able to formalize this problem algorithm these are the step-by-step procedure guaranteed
to finish it requires a definiteness effective computability and finiteness finiteness so then
you write program you are actually expressing the algorithm using a computer language this
is very high level language there are also low level languages and you have instructions
at architecture specifies the set of instructions the computer can perform at that level you
must define the data types addressing modes etc
micro architecture is a detailed organization of a processor implementation
different implementations of
a single is there are different implementations of a single instruction set architecture this refers
to organization we have a certain architecture but we might have many different organizations
and we use logic circuits at that level
these are the basically com combination of basic operations to realize micro architectures at that
level we have many different choices
but this was a good talk for today if you have any questions please feel free to reach out to me
in the comments or on the chat screen we have been also having questions regarding various
projects and discussions how these projects can be implemented and how to use them
so we should use the material and the application as well
and they could be applied in real-time or they do not apply when we are working with virtual machines
repeated same concept at the different angles three times but just to make sure that we have
the concept these are refers to control architecture and organization basically
so to to exemplify you want to solve a system of equations okay
this partial differential equation probably
that's the only model of differential equations lets just show the example
there are different algorithms to solve to solve this partial differential equation
this is subject of numerical methods either you can use red black s o r kausin elimination
jacobi iteration multi-grid you don't have to understand this but these are
differential equation numerically
four different approaches
the our problem is
solving this differential
partial differential
equation
now we have to choose
an algorithm
we have four options
you have to choose
one okay
suppose that we have chosen Gaussian elimination
now
we are
at this stage
to choose the
coding
environment or programming
language we have
many options
we have more than
maybe 100 programming
languages but for the
timing as an example let's assume
that we have four options either
we can choose
from Fortran C
C++ or Java
let's assume
that we have chosen C
to implement this Gaussian elimination
now
we have to choose determine
which platform
hardware platform to implement
which architecture
we can choose
power PC architecture
there are many architectures as well but
as an example here we have only
three
architectures we can
choose either power PC
Intel architecture or
Atmel probably it uses
RISC architecture for embedded applications
if our application is
for embedded system then we will choose this
if it is general purpose either we will choose
power PC or Intel based
again it depends on availability
if you don't have a power PC based control system
you can use a power PC based control system
and all the other lotteries
however this gustaría
if you have a power PC place
competing system and it
you have no other option to choose. You will choose Intel.
mostly have Intel base then
I would recommend the
Suppose that we have chosen Intel architecture.
design one of them
of which I will explain you
in terms of accessibility
and its capabilities
Now we might
what I explained
can not be a little late
have different options depending
it comes need to be
a common
on, for example, computing performance
focus
when a device
is running
requirements. Either we can choose Sentinel, Pentium 4,
such that power
is vegetables
here you will see
or Xeon processor. Now we have more options.
me
For example, we can choose Ethereum, then that and 8 core, whatever core,
more advanced processors. But one key issue is
architecture is all
for all these three processors are the same,
but implementations are different. They use different organizations.
Assuming that we have chosen Pentium 4, now
we face with choosing the
addition algorithm.
Well, there might be a Pentium processor
in which addition is implemented
using ripple carry adder. What a ripple carry adder
is a subject of logic or digital design.
We have probably studied that. Or carry look ahead
adder. But what are the differences between these two?
Ripple carry adder is
slower than carry look ahead adder. But carry look
at adder consumes more power.
So probably there are some chips. If
primary
objective in this Pentium chip is
to be used in a mobile device or
lower power systems, then probably
it will use ripple carry adder. But if the criteria
is high performance system, then it will use carry look adder.
Anyway, assume that we have
chosen carry look at a Pentium 4
processor with carry look at adder.
Then now we have the implementation
of the chip options. We can use CMOS
or of course manufacturer probably use CMOS
to implement that Pentium or bipolar or gallium arsenide
or some other semiconductor technologies.
CMOS is complementary metal oxide
silicon.
Bipolar is a different technique which
this uses most transistors.
This uses bipolar transistors.
The gallium arsenide uses gallium arsenide
semiconductors materials.
The properties are these are silicon based.
CMOS consumes much less power
than the others, but they are slower.
Bipolar is faster, but
consumes more power than CMOS.
Gallium arsenide is
fastest of all, but
it requires a lot
of
power to operate.
Now we have
three options
here to choose with.
If our requirement is low power,
then we will go for this.
If it is moderate power and
higher speed, bipolar,
or if it is very specific
application,
then we will go for gallium arsenide.
So at all levels,
we have several choices.
So of course,
then we have trade-offs.
You have to balance
between cost,
performance,
and power.
Whichever is priority,
you will go for it.
Now we have
three options here.
Bipolar and
higher speed.
Bipolar and higher speed.
Bipolar and higher speed
are both
a problem and
a problem.
If the
Bipolar and higher speed
is a
problem,
the
Bipolar and higher speed
will be
a problem and
data we already know these concepts usually
we classify programming languages in terms of what anybody can tell me
probably when you study programming one two you have also seen this classification
programming languages are classified there are several classifications but in terms of the
running environment we classify programming languages in what classes anybody can tell me
before we finish this lecture
how do you classify programming languages
high level and low this is the classifications
another class in terms of the programming environment
here we see some of the c fortran other basic java
object oriented or this is another classification as i said many classifications but i am
specifying in terms of the programming environment
okay we have
compilers for some languages
this is probably a hint
and we have
have interpreters for some other languages some languages are classified as compiled languages
some are classified as interpreted languages what are the difference between compiled and
interpreted languages in compiled languages you code it you don't run it you compile it
using a specific architecture then you link it and you have the assembler and you have an executable
file then you will be able to run that program after executable file the your program will be
mapped to instruction set architecture then you will have implementation on whatever hardware is
your program will run
another type of languages such as basic or some modern languages like MATLAB or Python or Perl
whatever they can be considered as interpreter they run while you write you have a runtime
environment or interpreter then it will run directly you don't have a compilation
stage and these type of languages are known as interpreted languages you have an interpreter
it runs while you type then you have a third class platform independent neither compiled
or nor interpreted but platform independent it is java is such a platform independent language
language in the compiled languages you have the code then at the end you have an executable
program which in terms of the instruction set architecture but in java we have a compiler
following steps
you don't have an executable code in terms of the instructions as a repository opinion
code even though java can be convenient and we have was but in these hypothesis which make things
true we don't have the language that demands code you do we don't want to add code again
it would also benefit the generously explodes because if you don't put anyמה says something
that these explanationsburني whether this you will be difficult for you which is true and
instruction set architecture you have a bytecode generic bytecode actually you can write a java
program in a platform and you can take this program and without any modification you can run
it on other platform you write in macintosh you can write you can run on ibm how this happens
actually java compiler produces a bytecode and this bytecode is in
interpreted in the specific machine to be able to run on that machine which takes this bytecode
and translates into instruction set architecture of course to be able to run these java programs
we have to have java runtime environment still you need some sort of interpreter but
if java is classified as platform independent language in this respect
Perl is neither compiled nor interpreted in between it can be compiled it can be interpreted
I think python is the same as well so it can be interpreted it can be compiled
they are called scripting languages
okay we stop here do you have any question
any comment next week we will continue with some more technical definitions
then probably
within two weeks we will start discussing the actual algorithms
no question I have to finish here because in five minutes I have another meeting see you next week
see you next week
bye